Guide to the Blackwell Family Papers, 1845-1976 and undated RL.11058
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Blackwell family papers
1845-1976 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Blackwell family
Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1857-1950
Blackwell, Anna, active 1875-1876
Blackwell, Elizabeth, 1821-1910
Blackwell, Henry Browne, 1825-1909
Stone, Lucy, 1818-1893
Ross, Ishbel, 1897-1975
RL.11058
1.6 Linear Feet 136 items
Collection contains primarily correspondence and printed materials. There are also three unidentified and undated black-and-white photographs, along with a few items representing the Livingston family, including a genealogy developed by Helen Thomas Blackwell. The correspondence contains mostly routine letters to Blackwell family members from other family members; including Alice Stone Blackwell, Anna M. Blackwell, Elizabeth Blackwell, Emma Blackwell, Helen Blackwell, Henry B. Blackwell, and Lucy Stone. There are also several postcards mailed to the Woman's Journal regarding subscriptions, address changes and other matters related to publication, or the editor's business acquaintances. There are several printed materials written by Blackwell authors, including "Philosophy of Re-Incarnation" by Anna Blackwell, and "Medicine & Morality," "Scientific Method in Biology," and “Erroneous Method in Medical Education" by Elizabeth Blackwell. However, the series primarily features printed items that were maintained in the Blackwell family library. Also contains a corrected typescript (1940s) of Ishbel Ross' Life of Elizabeth Blackwell along with notes from 1958 on the Elizabeth Blackwell award at Smith College.
Arrangement
Arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Photographs, Livingston family papers, Printed Materials, and Manuscripts.
Biographical Note
Samuel Blackwell, a sugar refiner and lay preacher, emigrated to the United States from England in 1832, with his wife Hannah (Lane), eight children, and a governess. Their youngest child was born in New York City; they moved to Newark, N.J., then to Cincinnati, Ohio. Of the nine children, three are represented in this collection, Anna Blackwell, the poet, translator, and journalist; Elizabeth Blackwell (1821-1910), the pioneering physician; and Henry B. Blackwell (1825-1909), an editor, journalist, and businessman. Also represented is his wife, suffragist Lucy Stone, and their daughter, Alice Stone Blackwell. In addition, there are materials from Lucy's niece, Emma Stone Lawrence, who eventually married George Washington Blackwell, another of the nine children of Samuel and Hannah Blackwell. There are items from their daughter, Anna M. Blackwell, who went on to marry Charles Belden, librarian of the Massachusetts State Library, in 1908, as well as from Helen Thomas Blackwell, who married Anna’s brother, Howard.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Blackwell Family Papers, 1845-1976 and undated, were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2017.
Collection Overview
Collection contains primarily correspondence and printed materials. There are also three unidentified and undated black-and-white photographs, along with a few items representing the Livingston family, including a genealogy developed by Helen Thomas Blackwell. The correspondence contains mostly routine letters to from other family members to Alice Stone Blackwell, Anna M. Blackwell, Elizabeth Blackwell, Emma Blackwell, Helen Blackwell, Henry B. Blackwell, and Lucy Stone. There are also several postcards mailed to the Woman's Journal regarding subscriptions, address changes and other matters related to publication, or the editor's business acquaintances. There are several printed materials written by Blackwell authors, including "Philosophy of Re-Incarnation" by Anna Blackwell, and "Medicine & Morality," "Scientific Method in Biology," and “Erroneous Method in Medical Education" by Elizabeth Blackwell. However, the series primarily features printed items that were maintained in the Blackwell family library. Also contains a corrected typescript (1940s) of Ishbel Ross' Life of Elizabeth Blackwell along with notes from 1958 on the Elizabeth Blackwell award at Smith College.
Black-and-white photographs; Cabinet photographs; Typescripts; Genealogies (histories); Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1857-1950; Blackwell, Anna, active 1875-1876; Blackwell, Elizabeth, 1821-1910; Blackwell, Henry Browne, 1825-1909; Ross, Ishbel, 1897-1975; Stone, Lucy, 1818-1893; Blackwell family; Blackwell family -- Library; Livingston family; Woman's journal (Boston, Mass.: 1870); Lisa Unger Baskin Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library); Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Correspondence, 1845-1969 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Comprises mostly routine correspondence to Blackwell family members from other family members; including Alice Stone Blackwell, Anna M. Blackwell, Elizabeth Blackwell, Emma Blackwell, Helen Blackwell, Henry B. Blackwell, and Lucy Stone. Topics include suffrage meetings, the election of Theodore Roosevelt, reading and other pastimes, and general education. A letter from Henry B. Blackwell mentions inviting Frederick Douglass and his wife, Helen Pitts Douglass (editor of The Alpha, suffragist, feminist, abolitionist) "to some private house, where his color would not be made an objection" written on Office of American Woman Suffrage Association letterhead. There are several postcards mailed to the Woman's Journal regarding subscriptions, address changes and other matters related to publication, or the editor's business acquaintances.
  - Alice Stone Blackwell, 1892-1909 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anna M. Blackwell, 1905-1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Elizabeth Blackwell, 1845 and undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter and notes on Irish Home Rule and Gladstone's policies (Folder 1)
      Material comprises a letter Blackweel wrote to an unidentified gentleman, probably between 1880-1895, following her retirement from the medical profession. During this time, Blackwell was actively involved in many different reform movements, including women’s rights, antivivisection, sanitation, and moral reform. This letter contains Elizabeth Blackwell’s lengthy critique of William Ewart Gladstone’s 1886 Irish Home Rule Bill. Blackwell’s letter begins: ‘Dear Sir, No one desires more strongly than I, that a just system of Irish government should be substituted for the unjust “Castle” system. I therefore profoundly regret that Mr. Gladstone has not been able to see that his present scheme destroys the Imperial Parliament, and insists upon treating the absence of Irish members as a “detail.” I can only hope therefore that the Govt. Bill will be thrown out, and that no member supporting it, will be returned to Parliament.” William Ewart Gladstone, served as Prime Minister four separate times: (1868–1874, 1880–1885, February–July 1886 and 1892–1894). In early 1886, Gladstone proposed Irish Home rule but this was defeated in the House of Commons in July. Four other pages of undated notes on the topic accompany the letter. Includes a transcript for the letter.
  - Emma Blackwell, 1904-1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Helen Blackwell (Mrs. Howard L. Blackwell), 1934-1969 and undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Henry B. Blackwell, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lucy Stone, 1888-1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Woman's Journal or editor Agnes E. Ryan, 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Other letters, 1885-1919 and undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Photographs, undated; 0.1 Linear Feet
  Contains three uncaptioned black-and-white photographs. Two are cabinet cards. Images feature two unidentified women, a baby, and a dog.
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Livingston family papers, 1934-1976 and undated; 0.1 Linear Feet
  Contains a 1972 Livingston family genealogy created by Helen T. Blackwell along with an undated article on the disputed authorship of "'twas the Night Before Christmas," possibly written my Major Henry Livingston Also includes original poetry by Jeannie Livingston Hubbard Denig, 1934-1976.
  - Genealogy and article, 1972 and undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Poetry by Jeannie Livingston Hubbard Denig, 1934-1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Printed material, 1847-1958 and undated; 0.4 Linear Feet
  Series comprises a few printed materials written by Blackwell authors, including "Philosophy of Re-Incarnation" by Anna Blackwell, and "Medicine & Morality," "Scientific Method in Biology," and Erroneous Method in Medical Education" by Elizabeth Blackwell. However, the series primarily features printed items that were maintained in the Blackwell family library. Also contains a corrected typescript (1940s) of Ishbel Ross' Life of Elizabeth Blackwell along with notes from 1958 on the Elizabeth Blackwell award at Smith College.
  - Blackwell family authors: Anna Blackwell, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Blackwell family authors: Elizabeth Blackwell, 1881-1898 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Blackwell family owned, 1847-1902 and undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Blackwell family owned, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Elizabeth Blackwell award, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Corrected typescript, Life of Elizabeth Blackwell, by Ishbel Ross, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 6)